Narrator: Part 1
Interviewer: Today, I’m talking to acclaimed playwright Diane Samuels,
whose play Kindertransport is widely considered a modern classic
and is now a set exam text for secondary school students.
Diane: Hello.
Interviewer: Diane, you were formerly a drama teacher, is that right?
Diane: Yes, that’s right.
Interviewer: Earlier this week, you may have heard one of our most respected Shakespearean actresses,
Dame Helen Mirren, announce somewhat controversially in a TV interview
that it’s a waste of time for children to read Shakespeare plays at school,
that Shakespeare must be brought alive through watching plays or films.
At the same time, some recently published research carried out in four large
London secondary schools tells a different story.
It concludes that, even though, inevitably,
some students think Shakespeare is boring and irrelevant,
many others say that they really enjoy reading and studying Shakespeare
– and these students don’t see the complexity of his language as a barrier,
more as an interesting challenge.
Diane, can I ask you, first of all, did you study Shakespeare at school?
Did you have a good or bad experience?
Diane: I remember studying Macbeth when I was about 15,
and I studied Hamlet for A level, and King Lear.
It was in the 1970s, so – in a Jewish comprehensive school in Liverpool,
and we would read the play aloud and talk about it a bit.
We didn’t act any of it out really, but I just…I did enjoy reading it aloud together in class.
It’s a very simple thing to do,
but you know that feeling of just reading something and airing it together?
I mean, there’s always the issue, isn’t there, of who gets which roles to read,
some people were more confident readers than others.
So, it was enjoyable, and I also...one of the other things that I remember was, for exams,
you obviously needed to remember the play, and I did enjoy
– maybe I enjoyed this more than anything
– learning soliloquies or learning quotes and kind of walking around my bedroom
or walking to school saying them over to myself.
Interviewer: And did you teach Shakespeare when you were a drama teacher?
Diane: When I was a drama teacher, I wasn’t required to teach Shakespeare at all.
I taught in inner London secondary schools in the 1980s
and Shakespeare wasn’t on the GCSE syllabus, as it was just coming in in those days.
So, you weren’t required to teach Shakespeare at all in drama.
Interviewer: Incredible.
Diane: But I did … I wanted to bring it to the students.
I taught for three years in a school called Hackney Downs,
which was a boys’ school in Hackney – it doesn’t exist anymore
– and...I’m always exploring the dynamics of it.
I like choosing a very particular scenario and then letting the whole play come alive through that scenario.
So, what I did was, I went into role as Desdemona,
and I didn’t tell them anything about Othello, about the play,
and I just sat in front of these 15-year-old boys and I put them in role and I said,
‘I want you to come to...to give advice.
I want you to be like counsellors or advisers for this young woman who’s got a problem.’
And I didn’t tell them any more than that,
and then I told them about how my handkerchief had gone missing,
and what would I do if my husband had given it to me,
and we just got into the play by this very little thing.
Interviewer: How did your students respond?
Diane: They just came to all these conclusions,
and they ended up actually voicing the things Othello voiced, like,
‘Well, are you having an affair with Cassio?’
And they became really suspicious,
and I didn’t do anything but ask their advice about the handkerchief,
and it was very interesting, the way the dynamic of the play,
just through this one character with this problem, sort of came alive in the role-play,
and I really enjoyed doing that.
And they then wanted to know a lot more about the play, but they were not coming at it as a text.
They were coming at it as a kind of living thing that was about people with struggles,
and it was very enjoyable and they really completely got it, it was brilliant, on an emotional level.
So they went at it, if you like, emotionally and physically rather than intellectually.
Interviewer: Absolutely.
So what do you think about Helen Mirren’s opinion, that reading Shakespeare in the classroom is a waste of time?
Diane: I’m always cautious, in terms of learning,
to say anything is a waste of time, ’cause it depends how you do it.
I’m sure Helen Mirren, coming at it as an actress, is in a way not saying it’s a waste of time,
but there’s better things you could be doing with your time.
And I have to say, in teaching Shakespeare, I do think what you want to do is get to the drama.
Yeah, it is live theatre and I would always err on the side of going for it on the floor,
if you like, first, and I tend to start a session, personally, working with Shakespeare,
getting people standing up in a space.
But then, I was trained as a drama teacher, and I make theatre, and I,
in my writing workshops that I run for all ages, I tend to get people playing and moving around,
or if they’re sitting around I get them into active-mode writing.
So, yeah, I think bringing it alive, getting into…the characters are great,
you know…getting into the language as it lives is probably more exciting
and multidimensional than reading it off the page.
But then there’s moments when just sitting quietly
and sitting with the language and looking at it can be fruitful, too,
so I think there’s probably a place for everything. I wouldn’t write it off completely.